window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Operating_System - Operating_System — Slot 23 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Operating_System — Slot 23",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is/are advantage(s) of virtual memory? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Faster access to memory on an average.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Processes can be given protected address spaces.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Linker can assign addresses independent of where the program will be loaded in physical memory.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Program larger than the physical memory size can be run.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Processes can be given protected address spaces.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1489/gate1999-2-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>A multi-user, multi-processing operating system cannot be implemented on hardware that does not support <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Address translation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>DMA for disk transfer</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>At least two modes of CPU execution (privileged and non-privileged)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Demand paging</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Address translation</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1488/gate1999-2-10\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>System calls are usually invoked by using <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a software interrupt</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>polling</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>an indirect jump</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a privileged instruction</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>a software interrupt</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1464/gate1999-1-11-ugcnet-dec2015-ii-44\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following disk scheduling strategies is likely to give the best throughput? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Farthest cylinder next</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Nearest cylinder next</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>First come first served</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Elevator algorithm</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Nearest cylinder next</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1463/gate1999-1-10\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Listed below are some operating system abstractions (in the left column) and the hardware components (in the right column)<br>\\(\\small \\begin{array}{cl|cl}\\hline \\text{(A)}&amp; \\text{Thread} &amp; \\text{1.}&amp; \\text{Interrupt} \\\\\\hline \\text{(B)}&amp; \\text{Virtual address space} &amp; \\text{2.}&amp; \\text{Memory} \\\\\\hline \\text{(C)} &amp;\\text{File system} &amp; \\text{3.} &amp;\\text{CPU} \\\\\\hline \\text{(D)} &amp;\\text{Signal} &amp; \\text{4.}&amp; \\text{Disk} \\\\\\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(A) - 2 (B) - 4 (C) - 3 (D) - 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(A) - 1 (B) - 2 (C) - 3 (D) - 4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(A) - 3 (B) - 2 (C) - 4 (D) - 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(A) - 4 (B) - 1 (C) - 2 (D) - 3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(A) - 3 (B) - 2 (C) - 4 (D) - 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1462/gate1999-1-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>If an instruction takes \\(i\\) microseconds and a page fault takes an additional \\(j\\) microseconds, the effective instruction time if on the average a page fault occurs every \\(k\\) instruction is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(i + \\dfrac{j}{k}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(i +(j\\times k)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{i+j}{k}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(({i+j})\\times {k}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(i + \\dfrac{j}{k}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1691/gate1998-2-18-ugcnet-june2012-iii-48\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider \\(n\\) processes sharing the CPU in a round-robin fashion. Assuming that each process switch takes \\(s\\) seconds, what must be the quantum size \\(q\\) such that the overhead resulting from process switching is minimized but at the same time each process is guaranteed to get its turn at the CPU at least every \\(t\\) seconds? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(q \\leq \\frac{t-ns}{n-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(q \\geq \\frac{t-ns}{n-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(q \\leq \\frac{t-ns}{n+1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(q \\geq \\frac{t-ns}{n+1}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(q \\leq \\frac{t-ns}{n-1}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1690/gate1998-2-17-ugcnet-dec2012-iii-43\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>A computer has six tape drives, with n processes competing for them. Each process may need two drives. What is the maximum value of n for the system to be deadlock free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1669/gate1998-1-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A counting semaphore was initialized to 10. Then 6P (wait) operations and 4V (signal) operations were completed on this semaphore. The resulting value of the semaphore is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>12</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1668/gate1998-1-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>When the result of a computation depends on the speed of the processes involved, there is said to be <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>cycle stealing</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>race condition</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a time lock</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a deadlock</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>race condition</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1667/gate1998-1-30\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Each Process \\(P_i, i = 1\\ldots 9\\) is coded as follows<br><pre><code> repeat \n    P(mutex)\n    {Critical section}\n    V(mutex)\nforever</code></pre> <br>\nThe code for \\(P_{10}\\) is identical except it uses V(mutex) in place of P(mutex). What is the largest number of processes that can be inside the critical section at any moment? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2264/gate1997-6-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>An operating system contains 3 user processes each requiring 2 units of resource R. The minimum number of units of R such that no deadlocks will ever arise is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>6</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2263/gate1997-6-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Dirty bit for a page in a page table <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>helps maintain LRU information</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>allows only read on a page</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2241/gate1997-3-10-isro2008-57-isro2015-64\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Thrashing <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>reduces page I/O</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>decreases the degree of multiprogramming</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>implies excessive page I/O</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>improve the system performance</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>implies excessive page I/O</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2240/gate1997-3-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>When an interrupt occurs, an operating system <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>ignores the interrupt</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>always changes state of interrupted process after processing the interrupt</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>always resumes execution of interrupted process after processing the interrupt</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>may change state of interrupted process to 'blocked' and schedule another process.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>may change state of interrupted process to 'blocked' and schedule another process.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2239/gate1997-3-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
